Curtis Thomas

curtisrthomas42@gmail.com

PROFILE

I currently work as a library media specialist at two elementary schools in Springfield, Missouri. In that role, I encourage and foster a love of reading in my students, teach them valuable information literacy skills, and provide them access to and training on technology tools that support their learning. I also support and collaborate with the faculty at each school by providing resources that relate to their curriculum and providing information and training on technology that they can use to enhance lessons, projects, and student outcomes in their classrooms.

I made the transition from a high school English and journalism teacher to a librarian because I wanted to share my love of reading, as well as my interest in technology that can help teachers and students accomplish their goals, showcase their learning, and express their ideas and passions. I also value digital citizenship and information literacy, particularly news literacy, and believe the library has a key role to play in providing those skills to students. As a librarian, I am able to combine my expertise as an English teacher, with experience teaching writing, research, news literacy, and video production.

EDUCATION

Hillcrest High School, Springfield, MO — 2009

Missouri State University, Springfield, MO — Bachelor of Science in Education, 2012

University of Missouri, Columbia, MO — Master of Arts in English, 2016

University of Missouri, Columbia, MO — Educational Specialist in Learning Technologies and Design with an Emphasis in Technology in Schools, ongoing

EXPERIENCE

Library Media Specialist, Westport Middle School, Springifeld, MO — Present

My role at Westport is a reading champion, instructional coach and collaborator, digital citizenship and civics advocate, blended learning specialist, and much more. As a middle school librarian, I buy, curate, and promote our reading collection, work with teachers to support their curriculum with resources and lessons, and provide technology support to students and staff.

Library Media Specialist, Sequiota and Bissett Elementary Schools, Springfield, MO —2018-2020 I worked as the library media specialist at two elementary schools in the Springfield R-12 school district. In that position I taught one lesson a week to every class at each school, focusing on literature appreciation, research/inquiry, library skills, and technology. I also managed each school's library collection and provide tech support to students, tracking spare Chromebook loans and repair tickets. I provided support to teachers as well, curating supplementary books, online resources, and other technology tools, training teachers when necessary on how to use tech in the classroom.

English / Composition / Journalism Teacher, Hillcrest High School, Springfield, MO — 2016-2018 In addition to teaching English and journalism courses, I also advised the school's yearbook staff and guided them through the process of designing, creating, and selling the school's yearbook. Some of the courses I taught include English III and English III H, Grammar and Composition, and Film as Literature. I have extensive experience teaching research, citation, writing, news consumption and production, and video/media production.

Graduate Instructor, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO — 2015-2016

As an instructor in the MU English Department, I taught English 1000—the introductory writing course all students are required to take. Through teaching this class, I gained additional experience teaching writing and research, and also gained a window into what colleges and college instructors are looking for in the students they accept and teach. We were given a great deal of freedom in how we teach the course; I chose the textbook for my classes, wrote the syllabus, and planned the assignments and lessons. Doing so has reemphasized to me the importance of working backwards when planning a course, deciding what I want my students to have learned by the end of the semester, designing

assignments that will teach them those skills, and planning lessons that will allow them to successfully complete those assignments.

Writing Tutor, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO — 2014-2015

During my first year at MU I worked ten hours a week at the campus writing center, tutoring on a one-on-one basis. While many students assumed we served as an editing service, our job was more focused on higher-order concerns, working with the student to improve the content, structure, and organization of their writing. Working as a tutor strengthened my one-on-one conferencing skills, something that I put to practice when helping students with assignments or to find the resources that best suit their needs.

Broadcast Journalism / Media Teacher, Central High School, Springfield, MO — 2012-2014 I taught classes on news media, film, and video production during my time at Central. This also included serving as advisor to the award-winning broadcast journalism group Central Intelligence, a bi-weekly student-led news program that produced content relevant to the students of Central. We attended and competed in national conventions across the country, and were also responsible for the school's end-of-the-year Memories Video. During my time there, Central Intelligence was also in charge of recording, editing, packaging, selling, and distributing all five high schools' graduation ceremonies—an incredibly huge undertaking. As my first experience as a professional educator, teaching at Central strengthened my belief in the importance of technology in the classroom to get students excited about learning and the importance of teaching students in any communication arts setting how to be "rhetorically flexible." That is, students should be able to identify their surroundings and the objects they contain (clothes, public spaces, images, video, body language) as "texts" that can be interpreted, and possess the ability to express that interpretation in a variety of genres and modes.

SKILLS

Working as a communication arts teacher with a teaching load that included courses in broadcast journalism, print journalism, media, and film has strengthened my ability to incorporate technology in the classroom. Podcasts, digitally-designed visuals, and other kinds of "writing" are great ways to get students to think critically, creatively, and make them more rhetorically flexible. I'm also a big believer in providing students as many "real-world" stakes in their projects as possible, and this applies to more traditional writing assignments.

My experience tutoring and teaching at the University of Missouri has given me a better sense of how to prepare students to be rhetorical flexible—the ability to successfully identify and adhere to the rules of any particular type of writing or meaning-making. It's vital that educators provide students the skills to think about form and genre by manipulating content in a variety of contexts. In my own writing course, I asked students to research a topic for an exploratory essay, then convert and expand that information for an argumentative essay, and then convert that information again and put it into some kind of visual presentation. This allows students to make comparisons between each kind of writing, examining how each genre asks them to present the same information in different ways and for different purposes.

Now, as a library media specialist, I'm able to use all of the skills I've developed to support teachers and students as they navigate the rhetoric they encounter online, create meaningful content of their own, and learn new technologies that allow them to express themselves, learn new things, and connect with others. The experience I've gained at each stage in my career as an educator have given me skills that I believe would make me an effective secondary school library media specialist.